Thank you to HelloFresh for sponsoring
this video. This is Andrew Huberman, the
internet's favorite neuroscientist.
Andrew Huberman.
Through his research at Stanford
University and his excellent podcast, he
has become the goto expert on the best
habits and routines for living a
successful and fulfilling life.
And this is me. While I don't think I
have the worst habits in the world,
lately I've been in a slump.
less energy throughout the day, slacking
off in healthy habits, and an inability
to focus on my work, leading to a
constant feeling like I'm going through
the motions at half speed. So, for the
next 30 days, I want to try Andrew
Huberman's sciencebacked morning routine
to see if it can pull me out of the rut
that I'm in. But what is Andrew
Huberman's morning routine? For me, I
tend to wake up sometime around 6:00
a.m., 6:30, and I write down the time in
which I woke up. The second thing I do
after I wake up is I make a beline for
sunlight. So, getting outside for a
10-minute walk or a 15-minute walk is
absolutely vital to mental and physical
health. We get back, I start craving
caffeine, but I purposely delay my
caffeine intake to 90 minutes to 120
minutes after I wake up. So, for me, I
just drink water. I also put a little
bit of sea salt in the water
and I also drink my athletic greens
which is compatible with fasting. So I
don't eat anything until about 11:00
a.m. or 12 noon. Next I would do a
90inute bout of work and that's
typically phone off and out of the room.
You'd be amazed how much you can get
done in 90 minutes if you are focused.
After I finish that cognitive workout, I
do some form of physical exercise for
about an hour. Very last, but certainly
not least, deliberate cold exposure.
And that's what I do each morning. And
I'm certain that these tools work.
On day one, I wake up craving coffee.
However, instead, I get ready and I head
out from my morning walk. And while it's
definitely no morning coffee, it
actually is really, really nice. and I
feel pretty good afterwards.
What doesn't feel so good though is
drinking salt water.
But I don't want to rely on how I'm
feeling to evaluate my progress on this
goal as feelings can change pretty
quickly. I don't want to do this. I
don't want to do this. Here we go.
To track my progress with this
challenge, I'm going to be conducting
three tests. The first is I just took a
blood test for day one. That's going to
measure things like my testosterone
levels and judging by how scared I was
to prick my finger.
Oh, I can't do it. I can't do it.
I'm worried they might be a little low.
Ow.
Test number two is by tracking my energy
and my mood levels at the end of each
day. I've already been doing this for
the past month. So, at the end of this,
I'm going to compare my numbers and see
if I've made any improvements. And
finally, I'll be testing my work
productivity. To help me evaluate that,
I've asked for help from the one person
who knows my work habits better than
anyone else.
My name is Brendan. I am Cam's brother
and his boss.
You're not my boss.
I'm evaluating how you do at your job.
That makes me your boss.
Just talk about my work habits.
Sure. You procrastinate. Get distracted.
Procrastinate more. Just a serial
scroller. Bad communication. bad time
management, missed deadlines.
Yeah, I think that sums it up.
And sadly, he's not wrong. I am terrible
at focusing. And in my first week in
this challenge, that seemingly has not
changed. Even with a sciencebacked
checklist to help, my brain is still
struggling to get into the zone and work
effectively. And even though it's still
early into this goal, I really need to
figure this out. For a bit more context,
I work from home most days. And if you
come through here, just got to come
through the bathroom, past the toilet,
and voila,
this is where I work. Staring at a
screen in a storage room closet that is
connected to
my bathroom. Now, I have done the best
to make this space feel cozy. However,
it is still kind of a shitty place to
work. no pun intended. And with that, I
become really good at getting out of
this room and distracting myself at any
chance I can get. Even with my phone out
of the room, I am getting up constantly
to top up on coffee or look for snacks
that I can't even eat because I'm
fasting. And with each of these
interruptions, I'm killing my momentum
when I try to dig into a task. And I'm
falling further and further behind in my
work. And this is definitely the area I
need to improve the most. Or at least
that's what I thought.
Testosterone,
that's your ideal range. 2.49
2.4.
I'm below average.
Gosh,
I am speechless. I am speechless.
So, one week in and I am failing in two
categories.
Great.
With the discouraging week one complete,
I really want to hone in on improving my
work sessions for week two. So, I decide
to revisit some Huberman Lab episodes to
see if there's any tweaks I can make to
improve my focus. Couple of things for
optimizing workspace that are grounded
in neuroscience and physiology. So what
I do is I prop the computer up such that
it's at least at eye level when our eyes
are directed upward. It creates a state
of heightened alertness. In addition, I
use low-level white noise turned on at a
low volume, not with headphones most of
the time, puts the brain into a state
that's optimal for learning and
workflow.
The one single perk of working in a
bathroom,
white noise is easy to come by.
I'm hoping that if I can pair as much of
Hubberman's advice on focus with the
rest of my morning routine that it can
put me in the best possible position to
lock in on my work and really start to
see some progress.
This feels crazy to say this early into
a challenge, but I feel like I'm already
noticing benefits from this strictly
from like an energy and mood standpoint.
I used to wake up every morning and just
like doom scroll Twitter and now I like
I genuinely look forward to these walks
but get some natural light in my eyes,
get some fresh air, some steps. I'm like
halfway through an audiobook that I
started this week.
Things are going well. Even with my cold
showers, while they're definitely not
fun during, I do feel energized
afterwards and it feels like it fuels
the rest of my day. This next blood test
is about to be
so much better.
But as much as I've seen improvement in
my energy and in my health, my work
sessions still seem to come up short.
If I'm being honest, there hasn't been
as much improvement as I was hoping.
It's hard to point to anything and say
you've accomplished more than you
normally do.
Determined to improve my performance, I
opted to switch where I was going to be
working and hopefully get myself into a
better zone for focused work.
[Music]
But after 3 days working out of my
house, my work still hasn't improved.
And it's starting to look more and more
like the problem isn't where I'm
working.
The problem is me. Yet another day where
I am not as productive as I should.
Just feels like the story of my life at
this point. Ever since I started working
for myself, ever since it's just me and
my computer in my house, like it is like
pulling teeth. It it it just feels like
my brain cannot do this. And I don't
know what that is, but it feels like
I've been fighting against the same
thing. number one problem in my life is
being able to work for myself, be
disciplined, be focused in my own work.
And I like it's been eight years of
fighting this same thing.
Like, how does it make any sense? It
starts to just feel like like it just
starts to feel like this
is who I am. Like, this is
like
maybe I'm just like not the person that
I thought I was. Maybe this is just like
it, you know, and that's that is scary.
And I just feel like I'm leaving so much
potential on the table for myself, for
my future. And that like that thought is
like horrifying, you know? Goodness
gracious.
Feeling
defeated, my only hope now is to try and
work backwards through the past two
weeks to hopefully try and figure out
what has been holding me back. Why is it
that everything feels like it's working
except for this one thing?
Ever since it's just me and my computer
in my house, it is like pulling teeth.
Just a serial scroller. halfway through
an audio book that I started this week
and I just feel like I'm leaving so much
potential on the table for myself, for
my future. Like that thought is like
horrifying.
Even though I've been working with my
phone off and out of the office, I am
still constantly using it throughout
this routine on my walks before I get
ready to work. And after my 90 minutes
are up, I immediately go to my phone.
And if I'm constantly distracting myself
before I sit down, it feels like I just
keep craving that distraction when I'm
working.
[Music]
The next morning, I decided to try
keeping my phone powered down until it
was time for my lunch break to see if it
would help me focus.
The moment you sit down to do some
serious work and you flip off the
internet, all of a sudden it's as if the
phone has a voice. But we all are
familiar with the fact that if we are
focused on something that we all that
just kind of melts away. So I'm creating
this space. I'm funneling my brain into
a state where I set up a relationship
not just between me and the work that
I'm doing, but between me and my ability
to control my own state of mind.
The more I avoided using my phone, the
more focused I felt, allowing me to move
throughout my mornings faster and more
productively.
And on the days where I really wanted to
use my phone the most, I straight up
stashed that in my car because I
need to focus.
And I have to say that while it can be a
challenge to try and achieve this state
and this tunnel of work, some days you
start to get kind of addicted to it. It
feels really good. It's like a workout
for the mind.
I don't remember the last time I had an
experience where I I feel like I was in
a flow state twice today. Twice. Oh, and
it feels good. I cannot say it enough.
That felt so good today.
As strange as this may sound, I feel
like the habit of jumping into cold
showers and drinking those awful salt
water drinks has actually made me more
resilient when it comes to distraction.
Because just practicing that daily habit
of doing something hard that I know will
be satisfying once it's over. It's
literally the exact same thing with
getting in focused work. It's hard. It's
challenging, but I feel so much better
than I have in some time. We got a 10 in
energy and a 10 in mood. That is the
first perfect day of this challenge.
Today was a good day. A really, really
good day. And when I tally up my numbers
from the last 30 days, there's been
improvement in both my energy levels and
my mood. With my reported energy levels
increasing almost two whole points.
Not just that you've turned in
everything on time this week, which I
appreciate. It's that it's really good
work.
Which leaves just one final test. Here
we go.
Day one. Day 30. Let's go.
I'm average.
Vitamin D got better. My cholesterol got
better.
Everything is better.
Things have been going so well, I even
started putting my friends onto the
routine.
I've been doing the Hummer morning
And how did you hear about it?
You told me about it. Hey, things have
been going so well that I am honestly
going to continue doing this. And I'm so
thankful that I gave this a try. And to
celebrate, on the final day, I invited
my brother and my friend Matt out to go
for a cold plunge to finish this off by
doing something challenging that I know
will feel good afterwards. And my hope
is that going forward after this
challenge that I can do that more often.
That I can force myself to do difficult
things that I know will pay off in time.
Let's go.